Guide to the Baldwin Federation Records, 1971 - 1985
Duke University. University Archives
Baldwin Federation records 1971 - 1985
Duke University. Baldwin Federation.
2.2 linear feet Extent: 2,200 Items
Duke University. University Archives
The Baldwin Federation was an undergraduate organization which united Alspaugh, Bassett, Brown and Pegram Residence Halls on the East Campus of Duke University from around 1971 to the early 1980s. Records contain minutes, constitutions, reports, ballots, correspondence, fliers, newsletters, a survey, a pamphlet, printed materials, photographs, and clippings. Major subjects include student life at Duke University, dormitories, residence and education, college freshmen, and the Joe Baldwin festival. Materials range in date from 1971 to 1985. English.
UA.31.16.0006
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Baldwin Federation Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975 and 1986.
Historical Note
The Baldwin Federation was composed of Alspaugh, Bassett, Pegram and Brown Residence Halls on Duke University's East Campus and was active from about 1971 until the early 1980s. Federation members established small special interest groups, hosted "Joe Baldwin" events, arranged concerts, and performed many one-act and full-length plays. Their residential education program featured several credit courses on subjects concerning twentieth-century American literature, sexuality, health care, and student relationships.
Three other Federations existed on campus around the early 1970s to the early 1980s: the Edens, Few, and Kilgo Federations. For the first time, independent living groups in several of the quadrangles on East and West campuses banded together to form college-type communities within the university setting. Faculty endorsed federations for their potential to help students realize their personal educational goals. Students supported federations because they provided a wider base for friendships and a variety of opportunities for involvement. A federation supplemented the on-campus living experience with a variety of house courses, occasional educational programs, festivals, dances, and parties. Each federation was headed by faculty who were responsible for organizing new programs, guiding governance of the federation structure, and facilitating partnerships among living groups.
In the early 1980s, federations were abolished in order to improve balance between men and women, and between selective and independent living groups on campus. While individual living groups were chartered and occasionally dissolved, the system of selective living, within the parameters of a program of residential living groups within residence halls, remained intact.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to the Baldwin Federation at Duke University from 1971-1983.
Subject Headings
College freshmen -- North Carolina -- Durham; College students -- Housing; Duke University. Alspaugh Residence Hall; Duke University. Baldwin Federation; Duke University. Bassett Residence Hall; Duke University. Brown Residence Hall; Duke University. Pegram Residence Hall; Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions; Dormitories -- North Carolina -- Durham; Residence and education; Student housing -- North Carolina -- Durham; Clippings; Photographs
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - Establishment and general governance materials, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The First Three Years, Baldwin history, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Federations -- Evaluation of the Three-Year Trial at Duke University, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baldwin Federation Constitutions, 1971, 1974, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1971-1975, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - General Council minutes, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Elections, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Elections, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Program III
    - Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Participant interviews, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Twentieth Century America course, evaluations and notes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Twentieth Century America course, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General activity planning materials
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Posters, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Drama Club, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Arts and Crafts workshop, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Joe Baldwin Festival materials, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Joe Baldwin Festival materials, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Event reports, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Holocaust speaker, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Joe Baldwin drama and music, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Fliers, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Daedalus program, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Federation leadership workshop, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Freshman Orientation Committee, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Baldwin Beat newsletter, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Baldwin Beat newsletter, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Baldwin Beat newsletter, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Pamphlet, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Community Voice newsletter, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Survey, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - There's No Place Like Home booklets, 1977-1978, 1979-1980, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Clippings, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
Related Material
Association of Independent Houses records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Alspaugh Residence Hall Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Bassett Residence Hall Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Brown Residence Hall Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Pegram Residence Hall Records.
University Archives, Duke University.